Diego Alburez-Gutierrez

Konrad-Zuse-Straße 1, 18057 Rostock, Germany

Email: alburezgutierrez@demogr.mpg.de Web: www.alburez.me; Twitter: @d_alburez

I am a social scientist specialising in inter-generational demography. My work has used mathematical modeling, micro-simulation techniques, and empirical analysis to explore changes in the experience of life events such as kin availability, family bereavement, and caring responsibilities across demographic regimes.

EDUCATION

The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

PhD, Demography and Population Studies

2014 - 2018

- Title: "Beyond excess mortality: the demographic life of a Mayan community after a war of massacres"
- Primary data collection: genealogical surveys and in-depth interviews (1 year fieldwork)
- Supervisors: Arjan Gjonça, Tiziana Leone, Ernestina Coast, and Michael Murphy

MSc, Social Research Methods (Distinction)

2013-2014

Practical approach with emphasis on quantitative and qualitative data analysis

Del Valle University, Guatemala

BA, Anthropology (First class/Summa Cum Laude)

2008-2012

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- Poster award (2021), Population Association of America Annual Meeting. Poster title: "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic in England and Wales." (Basellini, U., Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Del Fava, E., Perrotta, D., Bonetti, M., Camarda, C. and Zagheni, E.).
- Otto Hahn Medal (2019) awarded by the Max Planck Society for 'outstanding achievement from the initial creative period of young scientists'
- LSE PhD Academy Prize (2018) awarded by the London School of Economics for research on state-sponsored massacres in Guatemala
- LSE PhD Studentship (2014-2018) awarded by the London School of Economics

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany

Research Scientist (post-doc), Lab of Digital and Computational Demography

Jan 2019 - present

Research Area Chair, Lab of Digital and Computational Demography Sep 2019 - Sep 2021 Research-administrative role leading a group of four researchers in the 'Aging and Generational Processes' Research Area.

United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Denmark

Statistics Team Intern, Field Information and Coordination Support Section (FICSS) Mar - Jun 2018 Central role in implementing UNHCR's Demographic Projection Tool.

The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

Research Assistant, Law Department

Apr - Jul 2017

Leading qualitative research on low student satisfaction

Research Assistant, Social Policy Department

Mar 2016- Jun 2017

Quantitative analysis of maternal and child health outcomes in Palestine

Research Assistant, Sociology Department

Sep 2014 - Sep 2015

Qualitative coding and analysis of methodological practices in sociology of work

Research Assistant, Methodology Department

Oct 2013 - Jan 2014

Survey of grey literature to identify common qualitative methods in International Development

Public Opinion Program, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala

Lead researcher

Jul - Nov 2013

Designing and implementing qualitative research for the Media Monitoring Project

The Population Council, Guatemala

Research Sub Coordinator

Jan - Dec 2012

- Design and implementation of qualitative research on conditional cash transfer programmes
- Led team of four ethnographers during six months of data collection in rural Guatemala

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

International Max Planck Research School for Population, Health and Data Science (IMPRS-PHDS)

Class Teacher for course "Topics in Digital and Computational Demography"

2020 - present

European Doctoral School of Demography (EDSD), Barcelona

Class Teacher for course "Digital Demography"

2020 - present

The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

Class Teacher, Social Policy Department

2016-2017

- Leading seminars for the course "Introduction to Global Population Change"
- Weekly office hours, updated course website, homework and exam marking

Class Teacher, LSE Methods Summer School

2015

- Leading seminars for the "Qualitative Research Methods" strand
- Homework and exam marking

Del Valle University, Guatemala

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department

2013

- Leading seminars for the course "Advanced qualitative data analysis"
- Course design, homework and exam marking

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department Leading seminars for the course "History of Anthropology 1" 2011

PUBLICATIONS

(conventionally, the first author is the main author in social sciences)

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNALS

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (accepted). "The demographic drivers of grief and memory after genocide in Guatemala." *Demography*. Temporary doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-003.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Mason, C., and Zagheni, E. (2021). "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." *Population and Development Review*, 47(4): 997-1023. doi: 10.1111/padr.12436.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Kolk, M., and Zagheni, E. (2021) "Women's experience of child death: A global demographic perspective." *Demography*, 58 (5): 1715–1735. doi: 10.1215/00703370-9420770.
- Smith-Greenaway, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Trinitapoli, J, and Zagheni, E. (2021) "The Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: Indicators of the Cumulative Prevalence of Child Loss." *BMJ Global Health*, 6:e004837. doi: bmjgh-2020-004837
- Martinez-Folgar, K., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Paniagua-Avila, A., Ramirez-Zea, M., Bilal, U. (2021). "Excess Mortality during the COVID-19 Pandemic in Guatemala". *American Journal of Public Health*, 0:e1-e8. doi:10.2105/AJPH.2021.306452.
- Basellini, U., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Del Fava, E., Perrotta, D., Bonetti, M., Camarda, C. and Zagheni, E. (2021). "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic in England and Wales." SSM Population Health, 14. doi: j.ssmph.2021.100799.
- Riffe, T., Acosta E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, the COVerAGE-DB team. (2021) "Data Resource Profile: COVerAGE-DB: a global demographic database of COVID-19 cases and deaths." *International Journal of Epidemiology*, 50(2): 390-390f. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyab027.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (2021). "Vivir para contarla: un análisis demográfico de las masacres de Río Negro en Guatemala (1980-1982) [Living to tell the tale: A demographic analysis of the Rio Negro massacres in Guatemala (1980-1982)]." *Análisis de la Realidad Nacional*, 208:91–104. ISSN:2227-9113.
- Nepomuceno, M., Acosta, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Aburto, J.M., Gagnon, A., and Turra, C. (2020). "Besides population age-structure, health and other demographic factors can contribute to understanding the COVID-19 burden." *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*, 117(25). doi:10.1073/pnas.2008760117.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D**. (2019). Blood is thicker than bloodshed: A genealogical approach to reconstruct populations after armed conflicts. *Demographic Research*, 40(23): 627-656. doi:10.4054/DemRes.2019.40.23.
- Leone, T., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Gandour, R., Coast, E., and Giacaman, R. (2019). "Maternal and child access to care and intensity of conflict in the occupied Palestinian territory: a pseudo-longitudinal analysis (2000–2014)." Conflict and Health 13(36). doi:10.1186/s13031-019-0220-2.
- McGovern, P., and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez**. (2017) "Who takes workplace case-study methods seriously? The influence of gender, academic rank and PhD training." *Industrial Relations Journal* 48(2):98-114, doi:10.1111/irj.12171.

BOOK CHAPTERS

Alburez-Gutierrez, D., S. Aref, S. Gil-Clavel, A. Grow, D.V. Negraia, E. Zagheni. (2019). "Demography in the Digital Era: New Data Sources for Population Research." *Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the Italian Statistical Society.* doi: 10.31235/osf.io/24jp7.

TECHNICAL REPORTS

Alburez-Gutierrez, D. and Segura Garcia, C. (2018). "The UNHCR Demographic Projection Tool: estimating the future size and composition of forcibly displaced populations." *UNHCR Statistics Technical Series*: 2018/1. Copenhagen: United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.

REVISE AND RESUBMIT

- Castro, A. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "North and South: Naming practices and the hidden dimension of global disparities in knowledge production." R&R at *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*. Temporary doi:MPIDR-WP-2021-014.
- Stelter, R. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2022). "Representativeness is crucial for inferring demographic processes from online genealogies: evidence from lifespan dynamics." R&R at *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*.

WORKING PAPERS AND PAPERS IN PROGRESS

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Barban, N., Caswell, H., Kolk, M., Margolis, R., Smith-Greenaway, E., Song, X., Verdery, A., and Zagheni, E. (unpublished). "Kinship Approaches in Demography: Review and Key Areas for Future Development." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Basellini, U., and Zagheni, E. (unpublished) "When do parents bury a child? Uncertainty of offspring loss across the demographic transition." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.
- Snyder, M, **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Williams, I., and Zagheni, E. (2021). "The Lived Experience of COVID-19 Mortality: Quantifying the Relationship between Excess Mortality and Family Bereavement." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.
- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "Mortality change and its impact on child survival." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-001.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "DemoKin: An R package to implement matrix kinship models in stable and non-stable populations." https://github.com/IvanWilli/DemoKin.
- Theile, T., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, et al. (unpublished). "rSocsim: A multi-platform R package to run and analyse demographic microsimulations using SOCSIM."

INVITED TALKS (SELECTED)

- "The Demographic Drivers of Grief and Memory After Genocide in Guatemala." UW Seminar Series. Seattle, USA (University of Washington, 20 April 2021, online due to Covid-19).
- "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic." Mexico City, Mexico (El Colegio de Mexico, 16 April 2021, online due to Covid-19).
- "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." Population and Health Research Group Seminar Series, St Andrews, Scotland (University of St Andrews, 08 Dec 2020, online due to Covid-19).
- "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective." ISER External Seminar, Colchester, UK (Institute for Social and Economic Research, University of Essex, 27 November 2019).
- "The Demographic Foundations of the Lived Experience of Kin Death: A Genealogical Reconstruction." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University, 23 May 2019).
- "Ciencias Sociales Computacionales: Retos y oportunidades en la era digital [Computational Social Sciences: challenges and opportunities in the Digital Age]". Guatemala City, Guatemala (Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences, 25 April 2019).
- "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University, 8 February 2018).

OUTREACH AND SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

- News magazine: "Generational overlap places a heavy burden on parents in the global South" (News magazine of the International Union for the Scientific Study of Population, n-IUSSP, Jan 2022)
- News magazine: "Global trends in child loss: less and later" (News magazine of the International Union for the Scientific Study of Population, n-IUSSP, Nov 2021)
- Podcast episode: "Demografía y la experiencia de muerte [Demography and the experience of death]" (Divulga Podcast, episode 31, May 2021)
- Academic video: "How Can We Quantify the Immediate and Lingering Impact of Genocide on Local Populations?" (Latest Thinking, Apr 2020)
- Opinion piece: "Coronavirus: a warning to Latin America and the Caribbean to dramatically increase COVID-19 testing" (The Conversation, UK, Apr 2020)
- Blog post: "Genocide is the tip of the iceberg: Reviewing the Guatemalan case" (LSE Human Rights Blog, Feb 2016)

ORGANISER OF INTERNATIONAL ACADEMIC EVENTS

- Coordinator of the Seminar Series of the Lab of Digital and Computational Demography, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. 2020-2021
- Organiser and moderator: Panel Discussion on Digital and Computational Demography, IX Conference of the Latin American Association for Population Studies, Santiago, Chile (online) 2020
- Organiser: Rostock Open Science Workshop, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Rostock

• Organiser: Workshop on Demographic Research with Web and Social Media Data, 13th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), Munich 2019

SERVICE TO THE DISCIPLINE

- Reviewer for academic journals: Demography; Population and Development Review; Population Studies; European Journal of Population; Journal of Marriage and Family; Demographic Research; Revue Quetelet/Quetelet Journal; BMC Public Health; PLOS ONE; Scientific Reports; EPJ Data Science; International Conference on Social Informatics (SocInfo)
- Organiser of the 'Social Policy Qualitative Research Group', London School of Economics 2017-2018
- President of the 'Methodology Student Union', London School of Economics 2013-2014
- President of the 'Social Sciences Student Union', Del Valle University (Guatemala) 2011-2012

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP)
- British Society for Population Studies (BSPS)
- Population Association of America (PAA)
- European Association for Population Studies (EAPS)
- Latin American Association for Population Studies (ALAP)
- Latin American Studies Association (LASA)
- Households in Conflict Network (HiCN)
- Population Health and Armed Conflict Network (PHAAC)
- International Science, Technology, and Innovation Network of Guatemala (REDCTI)

SKILLS

- Statistical programming: R (base, tidyverse, data.table, parallel, shiny), Stata, Excel
- Text processing and web: IATEX, MS Office, (r)markdown, HTML, JavaScript, Tesseract
- Other programming: Git, Python 3, SQL, Hadoop
- Demographic microsimulation: SOCSIM with applications in R
- Qualitative data analysis: NVivo, Atlas.ti
- Experience in qualitative, quantitative, and online data collection

LANGUAGES

- International: **Spanish** (native), **English** (full professional C2), **German** (full professional C1), **Swedish** (beginner A1)
- Guatemalan: **K'iche'** (full professional C1), **Achi** (full professional C1), **Kaqchikel** (professional B1), **Q'eqchi'** (limited working A2)